Victor S. Clark Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Victor S. Clark Papers 1827-1944
MSS16014
Clark, Victor S. (Victor Selden), 1868-1946
4,500 items
11 containers plus 3 oversize
4.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Economist and author. Correspondence, financial statements, notes, clippings, reports on various areas and countries, and other data, largely pertaining to the Institute of Current World Affairs, Washington, D.C., and the world situation. Also includes papers of Levi and LeRoy Davis, farmers and merchants of the Genesee River Valley in New York, during the 1800s.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Blakemore, Thomas L., 1915- --Correspondence.; Clark family.; Clark, Victor S. (Victor Selden), 1868-1946.; Davis family.; Davis, LeRoy, 1836-1928.; Davis, Levi, 1807-1884.; Flanagan, Hallie, 1890-1969--Correspondence.; Hazard, John N. (John Newbold), 1909-1995--Correspondence.; Rogers, Walter S.--Correspondence.; Talbot, Phillips--Correspondence.
Organizations
Board of Research Associates in American Economic History.; Green and Davis.; Institute of Current World Affairs.; Puerto Rico. Insular Board of Education.; United States. Bureau of Mediation.
Subjects
Agriculture--New York (State); Economic history.; Economics.; Education--Puerto Rico.; Merchants--New York (State); Railroads--United States.; Social history.; World politics.
Places
Genesee River Valley (Pa. and N.Y.)--History.; Genesee River Valley (Pa. and N.Y.)--Social life and customs.; New York (State)--History.
Occupations
Authors.; Economists.
Provenance
The papers of Victor S. Clark, economist and author, were given or bequeathed to the Library of Congress by Clark between 1928 and 1951. A transfer of material from the Central Services Division was received in 1970.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Victor S. Clark are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1868, June 12 Born, Portageville, N.Y.
1890 Litt. B., University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, Minn.
1892 1893 Honorary fellow, University of Chicago, Chicago, Ill., studying at Göttingen University, Göttingen, Germany, and Bern University, Bern, Switzerland
1893 1897 High school principal and superintendent, Minnesota
1897 1898 Fellow, Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1899 1900 President, Insular Board of Education, Puerto Rico
1900 Director of public instruction, Puerto Rico Ph.D., Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1902 1906 Investigated tropical labor conditions, U. S. Bureau of Labor
1906 Published The Labour Movement in Australasia: A Study in Social Democracy. New York: H. Holt & Co.
1906 circa 1915 Head, Division of Manufactures and Economic History, Carnegie Institution of Washington, Washington, D.C.
1910 In charge of census, Hawaii (Ter.)
1910 1913 Commissioner, Board of Immigration, Labor and Statistics, Hawaii (Ter.)
1916 Published History of Manufactures in the United States. Washington, D.C.: Carnegie Institution of Washington
1917 1919 Director, Enemy Press Bureau, National Board for Historical Service
1917 1929 Member, Board of Research Associates in American Economic History, Carnegie Institution of Washington
1918 1929 Director, Brookings Institution Survey of Puerto Rico
1920 1928 Editor, The Living Age
1926 1944 Trustee, Institute of Current World Affairs, Washington, D.C.
1927 1932 Arbitrator, U. S. Board of Mediation
1930 Published with others, Porto Rico and Its Problems. Washington, D.C.: Brookings Institute
1929 1940 Consultant in economics, Library of Congress
1941 1946 Honorary consultant in economics, Library of Congress
1946, Mar. 30 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Victor Selden Clark (1868-1946) span the years 1827-1944. The papers are organized into the following series: Personal File, Family Papers, Special Files, Research and Writings File, and Oversize.
The Personal File, Special Files, and Research and Writings File series relate to Clark's career as an economist and author. The Special Files are largely comprised of records kept by Clark during his trusteeship of the Institute of Current World Affairs, and include such correspondents as Thomas L. Blakemore, Jr., Hallie Flanagan, John N. Hazard, Walter S. Rogers, and Phillips Talbot. Other papers reflect his membership on the Board of Research Associates in American Economic History of the Carnegie Institution of Washington, his work as an arbitrator on railroad cases for the United States Bureau of Mediation, and his service on the Insular Board of Education in Puerto Rico shortly after the territory was acquired by the United States in 1898.
The Family Papers contain farm diaries, business and land records, account books, daybooks, and financial records and legal papers relating to the firm of Green and Davis, Levi Davis, LeRoy Davis, and the Davis and Clark families especially in the Genesse Valley of New York. The Davis records were probably inherited by Clark through his mother Helen, who was a Davis before marriage.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in five series:
Personal File, 1882-1936
Family Papers, 1827-1929
Special Files, 1899-1944
Research and Writings File, 1837-circa 1941
Oversize, 1835-1913
Container List
- Personal File, 1882-1936 (Box 1)
  Correspondence, notebooks, account books, travel documents, legal papers, photographs, certificates and diplomas, memorabilia, newspaper clippings, and miscellaneous papers.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material and chronologically therein.
  - Certificates and diplomas, 1890-1913 See also Oversize (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1890-1929, undated (Box 1)
  - Legal papers, 1894-1898 (Box 1)
  - Letters and documents of reference and introduction, 1882-1923 (Box 1)
  - Memorabilia, 1890-1935 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1883-1928 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1897-1910, 1934-1936, undated (Box 1)
  - Notebooks and account books, 1887-1897 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1)
  - Travel documents, 1904-1933 (Box 1)
- Family Papers, 1827-1929 (Box 2-4)
  Correspondence, business and land records, financial records and legal papers, miscellaneous papers, and bound volumes of account books, farm diaries, and other records.
  Arranged by type of material and chronologically therein.
  - Correspondence, 1861-1915, undated (Box 2)
  - Business and land records of the firm of Green and Davis and of Levi and LeRoy Davis, 1833-1911, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Financial records and legal papers of the Davis and Clark families, 1863-1929 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1827, 1898-1900, undated (Box 2)
  - Bound volumes (Box 2)
    - Daybook of Levi Davis and the firm of Green and Davis, 1835-1849, 1857 See also Oversize (Box 2)
    - Invoice and account book of Levi Davis, 1835-1837, 1852-1861 (Box 2)
    - Account book of Levi Davis, 1836-1853 (Box 2)
    - Notebook (Box 2)
      - Records of the Union School Debating Society, Portageville, N.Y., 1847-1854 (Box 2)
      - Other entries, 1853-1860, 1874-1882 (Box 2)
    - Receipt book of Levi Davis, Genesee Valley Canal Warehouse, 1852-1862 (Box 3)
    - Account books of Levi Davis, 1854-1878, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Account book attributed to LeRoy Davis, 1861-1863 (Box 3)
    - "Album of Remembrance" of Mary J. Davis, 1863-1865 (Box 3)
    - Account book and farm diary of Levi Davis and LeRoy Davis, 1867-1884 (Box 4)
    - Memorandum book and farm diary of LeRoy Davis, 1871-1876 (Box 4)
    - Farm diaries of LeRoy Davis, 1876-1885 See also Oversize (Box 4)
- Special Files, 1899-1944 (Box 4-9)
  Reports, administrative records, correspondence, case files, financial records, orders and regulations, and miscellaneous documents.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic and alphabetically or chronologically therein.
  - Carnegie Institution of Washington, Board of Research Associates in American Economic History, Washington, D.C., 1902-1944 (Box 4)
  - Institute of Current World Affairs, Washington, D.C. (Box 4)
    - Antonius, George, 1931-1942, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Blakemore, Thomas L., Jr. (Box 4)
      - 1938-1940 (Box 4)
      - 1940-1941 (Box 5)
    - Brodie, Donald, secretary and treasurer, 1928, 1939-1940 (Box 5)
    - Crane, John O., 1926-1941 (Box 5)
    - Davis, Hallie Flanagan, 1943 (Box 5)
    - Flanagan, Hallie See same container, Davis, Hallie Flanagan (Box 5)
    - Grattan, C. Hartley, 1941 (Box 5)
    - Harper, Samuel N., 1932-1942 (Box 5)
    - Hazard, John N. (Box 5)
      - 1932-1937, (2 folders) (Box 5)
      - 1937-1939 (Box 6)
    - Herron, Francis, 1941-1944 (Box 6)
    - Hopper, Bruce C., 1927-1928, undated (Box 6)
    - Leland, Marine, 1942-1944, (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - May, Kenneth, 1937-1944 (Box 6)
    - Parkin, G. R. (George Raleigh), 1940-1943 (Box 6)
    - Powell, Helen K., 1943-1944 (Box 6)
    - Rogers, Walter S. (Box 6)
      - 1928-1935 (Box 6)
      - 1935-1941, (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - Simpson, Eyler N., 1927-1937 (Box 7)
    - Talbot, Phillips, 1938-1943, (3 folders) (Box 7)
    - Weidemann, Howard M., 1937-1939 (Box 8)
    - Witt, Lawrence W., 1940-1943 (Box 8)
    - Young, C. Walter, 1931-1939, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Puerto Rico, Insular Board of Education, 1899-1900, undated (Box 8)
  - United States Board of Mediation (Box 8)
    - Administrative and miscellaneous records, 1927-1930 (Box 8)
    - Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers v. Seaboard Air Line Railway Co., 1931 (Box 8)
    - Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Engineers v. Boston and Maine Railroad, 1929 (Box 8)
    - Brotherhood of Railroad Station Employees v. Boston and Maine Railroad, 1927 (Box 8)
    - Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen v. Boston and Maine Railroad, 1932 (Box 8)
    - Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen v. Erie Railroad, 1929 (Box 9)
    - Brotherhood of Railway and Steamship Clerks, Freight Handlers, Express and Station Employees v. Chicago and Northwestern Railroad, 1927 (Box 9)
    - Brotherhood of Railway and Steamship Clerks, Freight Handlers, Express and Station Employees v. New York Central Railroad and Grand Central Terminal, 1927 (Box 9)
    - Southern and Allied Federated Shop Crafts v. Southern Railway Co., 1929 (Box 9)
- Research and Writings File, 1837-circa 1941 (Box 9-11)
  Articles, essays, reports, student papers, short stories, book reviews, speeches, poems, travelogues, research notes, and printed matter.
  Arranged by type of material.
  - Articles, essays, and reports, 1933-1938, undated, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Book reviews, 1913-1940, undated, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 9)
  - Student essays and thesis, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, Minn., and Columbia University, New York, N.Y., 1890-1897, undated (Box 9)
  - Poems, 1898, 1908, undated (Box 10)
  - Short stories, undated (Box 10)
  - Travelogues, undated (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
    - Untitled book manuscript on a history of colonial Latin America, with notes, undated (Box 10)
    - Research notes on colonial Latin America, undated (Box 10)
    - Research file on economic crises in the American economy probably for "Past Crises in Retrospect and Contemporary Opinion," manuscripts and notes, 1932, (2 folders) (Box 10)
    - Untitled essay on money, with notes; "A Summer's Observations;" and "A Note on Japan's War Economy," 1938, undated (Box 11)
    - Research file on the international economy, circa 1941 (Box 11)
    - Transcripts of documents regarding the regulation of labor in Puerto Rico, 1837-1849 (Box 11)
    - Letter/essay, Clark to Elmer Thomas concerning Senate bill 5561, 1933 (Box 11)
    - Comments by Henry Broadhead, The Labour Movement in Australasia: A Study in Social Democracy, 1907 (Box 11)
    - Essay by H. D. Dickinson, "Judge Brewer and the Police Power," University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, Minn, 1890 (Box 11)
    - Printed copies of articles by Clark, 1902-1922, undated (Box 11)
- Oversize, 1835-1913 (Box OV 1-OV 3)
  Diploma, resolution, and farm diaries.
  Arranged and described according to the series, containers, and folder from which the items were removed.
  - Personal File (Box OV 1)
    - Certificates and diplomas (Box OV 1)
      - Diploma, 1890 (Container 1) (Box OV 1)
      - Resolution, Hawaii (Ter.), 1913 (Container 1) (Box OV 1)
  - Family Papers (Box OV 2)
    - Bound volumes (Box OV 2)
      - Daybook of Levi Davis and the firm of Green and Davis, 1835-1849, 1857 (Container 2) (Box OV 2)
      - Farm diaries of LeRoy Davis (Box OV 3)
        - 1876-1885 (Container 4), (2 vols.) (Box OV 3)